All right, so in this
section then, we're going
to talk about influencing
and team building.
All right, now, remember,
the project manager
is a visionary leader for the project.
They're the ones that are the making
decisions about the project.
So in a predictive environment, they are
the command and control project manager.
So they have influencing skills.
Project manager is going to
be influencing stakeholders
to make decisions on
what's best for the project.
Now, influencing does not mean forcing.
Don't ever think that, at least not for
the PNP exam.
Influencing means encouraging.
That's what influencing is, right?
You're encouraging,
you're collaborating with
stakeholders, encouraging
them to make the right decision.
And in this case, then, project managers
are going to influence stakeholders to do
what's best for the project, not
necessarily what's best for them.
But what's best for the project?
And that's a key skill then for a project
manager to have, influencing skills.
Now, there's four basic directions, right,
for influencing, these
four basic directions.
Upwards, downwards, sideways, and
outwards.
And this is something that's also covered
as part of communication management,
as well as part of stakeholder management
as well.
Because, again, who you're communicating
with, you're communicating
with stakeholders.
Who are you influencing?
You're influencing stakeholders.
And in this case, then, since we're
talking about the team, right,
you're going to be influencing team,
influencing your team.
So anyway, the four basic directions then
of influencing upwards, upward meaning
going towards senior
management, stakeholders
that are several pay
scales above you, right?
That's upwards communication or upward
influencing in this case.
And based on that,
you're going to be adjusting
your communication
style accordingly as well.
Then there's downwards, downwards towards
team members.
In this section, this is really what we're
talking about, what we're really covering,
is the downwards communication,
downwards towards team members.
Then you have sidewards communication,
right?
Sideward basically means peers,
a stakeholder peers or project managers,
peers within the organisation, and outward
means stakeholders
outside of the organisation.
And as a project manager, then,
as a visionary leader of the project,
you have influencing
skills, you're going to be
influencing all of your
different stakeholders.
Now, in this section, though, we are
talking about the team in particular, right?
So this is the downward influencing.
Now, as a project manager, you are the
lead of your team.
You are the coach of your team.
You want to get the best out of your team.
Your project is only as good as your team.
So first of all, you want your team
members to have the right skill sets.
But that's not enough.
You also want them to be working together.
If your team is not working together,
they will not be a good team.
Think of any sports team.
You may have all the best players in your
sports team, but if they're not working
together, they're not going to be a good
team.
And so that's entirely up to you now as a
project manager.
Right.
You want to develop your team,
right?
You want to engage your team, motivate
your team, inspire your team.
You are the coach of your team.
You are the lead of your team.
Again, your project is only as good as
your team.
So it's up to you now to develop the team.
Improved team competencies, improve team
interaction, all about collaboration.
You as a project manager, you have to
create that environment.
You have to create that culture within
your team.
team, if you like.
So open and effective communication,
team building, get your team members to
know one another, build trust amongst team
members.
Also, managing conflicts as well.
Right.
There are going to be conflicts between
team members.
That's inevitable.
Right.
So there's a separate video on a couple of
separate videos on conflict management.
Right.
But there's a difference between conflict
management and conflict resolution.
You can't always resolve a conflict,
team members will always disagree.
I mean, you know, you agree to disagree
type of thing.
So you can't always resolve a conflict,
but you can certainly manage a conflict.
And that's the biggest key here,
right?
Making sure that you actually manage the
conflict, right, rather than resolving in
it, managing it so it doesn't have a
negative impact on your, it doesn't have a
negative impact on your project,
right?
Thereby also encouraging collaborative
teamwork.
Team members can
still collaborate and work
together, even if they
disagree on the direction.
They might not always agree, but they can
still work together.
And again, that's up to you now,
as a project manager to create that
environment, right, to create trust
amongst one another.
And part of that then is also empowering
team members to make decisions.
It's not just a case of, all right,
you do this, you do this, you do this.
It's a case of also discussing
with team members,
you know, what work
needs to be done, right?
And so they can determine, you know,
the work that needs to be done.
They can be involved in estimating the
work that needs to be done.
And that's all done in an agile
environment anyway.
Remember, in an agile, it's always a
collaborative environment.
But even in a predictive,
even in a predictive
team members should work together, right?
They need to work together, again,
to make a good team.
So the people actually
doing the work should
be the one that's
estimating the work, right?
You don't just estimate the work by
listening to senior management, right?
So senior management
are just going to give you
some unrealistic budget,
some unrealistic deadline.
And if you're basing your project or
basing your plan on those unrealistic
figures, your project is already a
failure.
So your team members, subject matter
experts, they're the ones that you should
be getting estimates from,
whether it's a budget, timeline, the
work that needs to be done,
level of effort, whatever it is.
They're the ones that are the subject
matter experts.
They're the ones that know the work.
They're the ones that can
better estimate the level of
effort and the amount of
work that needs to be done.
So teams need to be involved in that kind
of decision making.
So again, You create this collaborative
atmosphere.
That calls for a much better project
experience.
Team members get to know one another.
And team members work together.
Again, just like any sports team.
If they're working together, they'll make
a fantastic team.
If they're not working together,
they'll make the worst team.
Now, as part of your role as a project
manager, is to assess your team.
And that's what this process here is
referring to team performance assessment.
It's assessing the team as a team.
a whole and individual team members.
So how is the team performing?
Are they doing the work that are supposed
to be doing?
Are they working efficiently?
How many tasks have been performed?
And then individual team members as well.
How well are individual team members
performing?
How well are they working with other team
members?
How well are they interacting?
That's all part of team performance
assessment.
And then part of that also is to basically
provide feedback.
positive and negative constructive
criticism when needed credit and feedback
when needed team members need to improve
the only way they're going to improve is
by you know letting them know areas of
improvement giving them this constructive
criticism not just you know demeaning them
that's not going to work anywhere you
don't demean team members what you do is
you know again it's all part of
encouragement It's
all part of influencing,
letting them know that
there's a skill gap here.
This is what they need to do to improve
their skills.
And that's how you learn.
You don't always learn by praising
someone.
You don't always learn by people
constantly praising you.
Now, obviously, that's important as well,
giving credit and feedback
when needed, right?
Because people need to be encouraged.
Giving praise to someone, obviously,
is going to encourage them.
but also areas of improvement as well.
What are your areas of improvement?
So constantly then evaluating performance
of team members.
Now, what if team members are not
performing?
Well, again, you talk to them,
you encourage them, you influence them.
Now, worst case scenario, extreme case,
if team members are really underperforming
and they're not going, obviously they're
not listening or not collaborating,
and you know really underperforming then
of course you can remove the
underperforming team member but that is
the last case scenario right so for the
purpose of the PMP exam that would be the
absolutely absolutely the last case right
where you actually replace the team member
or reassign the work first you work with
them you collaborate with them right you
encourage them you influence them.
If they, you know, if they're still not
pulling their weight, then, you know,
okay, if you need to reassign them,
then you reassign them.
But again, that would be the very,
you know, the very last thing.
Now a little blurb here on reward versus
recognition, right?
Those terms are generally used interchangeably,
but there is a subtle difference.
So if they ask you on the
exam, there is a very subtle
difference to, you know,
reward and recognition.
Generally, a reward is something that is
expected.
You have a goal, you meet this goal,
you get this reward.
It's like a bonus, for example,
right?
An example here, a sales goal is met,
you get a bonus.
And so you are working towards this bonus.
You know, if you make this sale,
you will get a bonus.
So you know if you work hard on this
particular activity or this particular
task, you do great, you are really
successful on this project.
You will get a promotion.
It's that expectation of promotion that
is, you know, really driving you to
perform really well because that is your
reward at the end of it.
A recognition, on the other hand,
is usually unexpected.
So you are performing the work,
right?
You're putting in long hours, you're
working hard to perform this work,
and you do a good job.
And then unexpectedly, you know,
your manager, whoever it is, they,
you know, they, you know, they appreciate,
they show your appreciation.
So they mention your name in a meeting,
for example, or you let your peers know,
or your superiors know, or they give you a
$100 gift card, for example.
Now, that $100 gift card was not expected,
right?
That was just unexpected.
Right.
You did not put in those long hours,
right?
You did not put in the
extra effort because
you were getting this
$100 gift card, right?
You put in the extra effort because you
needed to do the work.
You wanted to do a good quality job.
You put in the extra effort.
And then that was recognized.
If, on the other hand, your manager had
showed you this $100 gift card and said,
hey, you know, if you perform really well,
that $100 gift card is yours, well,
that would be a reward in that case.
So that's the basic difference then
between a reward and recognition.
Generally, a reward is expected, whereas
the recognition is usually unexpected.
So, again, I mean, you know, a lot of
these terms, like I said, are used
interchangeably, but just
as a very, very high level, just
in case in the exam they ask
you about the difference between
the two, that would
be the basic difference.